Delighted to be here
سعيد لوجودي هنا
and to talk to you about a subject dear to my heart,
و لأتحدث عن موضوع عزيز على قلبي،
which is beauty.
وهو الجمال.
I do the philosophy of art, aesthetics,
أعمل في فلسفة الفن و علم الجمال
actually, for a living.
فعليا للعيش.
I try to figure out intellectually,
أحاول أن أفهم بطريقة فكرية،
philosophically, psychologically,
فلسفية و نفسية
what the experience of beauty is,
ما هي تجربة الجمال،
what sensibly can be said about it
ماهو المعقول الذي يمكن قوله عن هذا الموضوع
and how people go off the rails in trying to understand it.
وكيف يذهب البعض بعيداً عن المسار في محاولتهم لفهم هذا الموضوع
Now this is an extremely complicated subject,
حاليا هذا الموضوع معقد جداً،
in part because the things that we call beautiful
بشكل جزئي ويرجع هذا لسبب وهو بأن الأشياء التي تسمى جميلة
are so different.
تختلف تماما عن بعضها البعض
I mean just think of the sheer variety --
أعني فكِر فقط في التنوع المطلق...
a baby's face,
وجه طفل،
Berlioz's "Harold in Italy,"
"هارولد في ايطاليا" لبرليوز،
movies like "The Wizard of Oz"
أفلام مثل "ساحر أوز"،
or the plays of Chekhov,
أو مسرحيات تشيخوف،
a central California landscape,
المنظر الطبيعي لوسط كاليفورنيا،
a Hokusai view of Mt. Fuji,
مشاهد هوكوساي لجبل فوجي،
"Der Rosenkavalier,"
أوبرا "Der Rosenkavalier" أو(فارس من روز)،
a stunning match-winning goal
هدف الفوز في مباراة مذهلة
in a World Cup soccer match,
لكأس العالم في كرة القدم،
Van Gogh's "Starry Night,"
"ليلة مرصعة بالنجوم" لفان غوخ،
a Jane Austen novel,
رواية جين أوستن،
Fred Astaire dancing across the screen.
رقص "فريد أستير" على الشاشة،
This brief list includes human beings,
هذه القائمة المختصرة تضم أشخاص،
natural landforms,
التضاريس الطبيعية،
works of art and skilled human actions.
أعمال فنية و بشرية ماهرة.
An account that explains the presence of beauty
تقرير يفسر وجود الجمال
in everything on this list
في جميع الأمور على هذه القائمة
is not going to be easy.
لن يكون بالأمر السهل
I can, however, give you at least a taste
ومع ذلك يمكنني أن أقدم لكم على الأقل نبذة
of what I regard
عما أعتبره
as the most powerful theory of beauty
أقوى نظرية في الجمال
we yet have.
لدينا في الوقت الحالي
And we get it not from a philosopher of art,
حصلنا عليها ليس من فيلسوف في الفن،
not from a postmodern art theorist
وليس من مُنظري فن ما بعد الحداثة
or a bigwig art critic.
أو ناقد عظيم في الفن.
No, this theory
لا، هذه النظرية
comes from an expert
تأتي من خبير
on barnacles and worms and pigeon breeding,
في البرنقيل و الديدان و تربية الحمام.
and you know who I mean:
وتعلمون من أعني بذلك..
Charles Darwin.
تشارلز داروين.
Of course, a lot of people think they already know
بطبيعة الحال ، العديد من الأشخاص يعتقدون أنهم يعرفون مسبقا
the proper answer to the question,
الإجابة الصحيحة على هذا السؤال،
"What is beauty?"
ما هو الجمال؟
It's in the eye of the beholder.
هي في عين الناظر
It's whatever moves you personally.
هو كل ما يحركك شخصيا.
Or, as some people,
أو حسب بعض الناس...
especially academics prefer,
خاصة الأكاديمين..يفضلون،
beauty is in the culturally conditioned
بأن الجمال يتكيف ثقافيا
eye of the beholder.
في عين الناظر
People agree that paintings or movies or music
يتفق الناس على أن اللوحات أو الأفلام أو الموسيقى
are beautiful
بأنها جميلة
because their cultures determine a uniformity of aesthetic taste.
بسبب ثقافاتهم التي حددت تماثل الذوق الجمالي
Taste for both natural beauty and for the arts
ذوق الجمال الطبيعي و الفني
travel across cultures
يتنقل عبر الثقافات
with great ease.
بسهولة كبيرة.
Beethoven is adored in Japan.
بيتهوفن هو معشوق في اليابان.
Peruvians love Japanese woodblock prints.
البيروفيون يحبون الطباعة اليابانية بالقوالب الخشبية
Inca sculptures are regarded as treasures
نحت "الإنكا" يعتبر من الكنوز الأثرية
in British museums,
في المتاحف البريطانية،
while Shakespeare is translated
بينما أعمال شكسبير تمت ترجمتها
into every major language of the Earth.
إلى كل لغة رئيسية على وجه الأرض
Or just think about American jazz
أو فقط فكر بالجاز الأمريكي
or American movies --
أو الأفلام الأمريكية...
they go everywhere.
الموجودة كل مكان.
There are many differences among the arts,
هناك العديد من الاختلافات في الفنون،
but there are also universal,
مع ذلك هناك أمور عامة،
cross-cultural aesthetic pleasures
بين الثقافات حول المتعة الجمالية
and values.
و القيم.
How can we explain
كيف لنا أن نفسر
this universality?
هذه العالمية؟
The best answer lies in trying to reconstruct
الإجابة المثلى تكمن في إعادة بناء
a Darwinian evolutionary history
تاريخ التطور الدارويني
of our artistic and aesthetic tastes.
في أذواقنا الفنية والجمالية.
We need to reverse-engineer
نحن بحاجة إلى إعادة هندسة
our present artistic tastes and preferences
أذواقنا الفنية و اختياراتنا الحالية.
and explain how they came
وشرح كيف جاءت
to be engraved in our minds
لتكون محفورة في أذهاننا.
by the actions of both our prehistoric,
الأفعال الموجودة في كلا العصرين ما قبل التاريخ،
largely pleistocene environments,
و الجليدي
where we became fully human,
حيث أصبحنا بها أناسا كاملين
but also by the social situations
و لكن أيضا بالمواقف الإجتماعية
in which we evolved.
التي تطورنا بها.
This reverse engineering
إعادة الهندسة هذه
can also enlist help
يمكنها أيضا أن تستمد العون
from the human record
من السجل البشري
preserved in prehistory.
المحفوظ في ما قبل التاريخ
I mean fossils, cave paintings and so forth.
أعني بذلك الحفريات، رسومات الكهوف وهكذا دواليك.
And it should take into account
وينبغي أن نأخذ في الإعتبار
what we know of the aesthetic interests
ما نعرفه عن المصالح الجمالية
of isolated hunter-gatherer bands
للعصابات البدائية المعزولة
that survived into the 19th and the 20th centuries.
و التي استمرت بين القرنين التاسع عشر و العشرين
Now, I personally
الآن، أنا شخصياً
have no doubt whatsoever
ليس لدي أدنى شك على الإطلاق
that the experience of beauty,
بأن تجربة الجمال،
with its emotional intensity and pleasure,
مع قوة العاطفة و السعادة
belongs to our evolved human psychology.
تنتمي إلى علم النفس البشري المتطور.
The experience of beauty is one component
تجربة الجمال هي عنصر واحد
in a whole series of Darwinian adaptations.
في سلسة كاملة من التعديلات الداروينية.
Beauty is an adaptive effect,
الجمال هو نتيجة التكيف،
which we extend
الذي ننشره،
and intensify
ونزيده قوة
in the creation and enjoyment
في صنع و متعة
of works of art and entertainment.
أعمال الفن و الترفيه.
As many of you will know,
العديد منكم يعلم بأن،
evolution operates by two main primary mechanisms.
نظرية التطور تعمل بآليتين أساسيتين،
The first of these is natural selection --
الأولى وهي الاصطفاء الطبيعي..
that's random mutation and selective retention --
هذا التغير العشوائي والاحتفاظ الانتقائي..
along with our basic anatomy and physiology --
جنبا إلى جنب مع أساسيات علم التشريح ووظائف الأعضاء..
the evolution of the pancreas or the eye or the fingernails.
تطور البنكرياس أو العين أو أظافر الأصابع.
Natural selection also explains
الاصطفاء الطبيعي يوضح أيضاً
many basic revulsions,
أمور اشمئزازية أساسية،
such as the horrid smell of rotting meat,
مثل الرائحة الفظيعة للحم المتعفن،
or fears, such as the fear of snakes
أو المخاوف مثل الخوف من الثعابين،
or standing close to the edge of a cliff.
أو الوقوف على حافة الهاوية.
Natural selection also explains pleasures --
الاصطفاء الطبيعي يتحدث أيضاً عن اللذات..
sexual pleasure,
المتعة الجنسية،
our liking for sweet, fat and proteins,
ولعنا بالحلوى، الدهون و البروتينات،
which in turn explains a lot of popular foods,
وهذا بدوره يفسر الكثير من المأكولات الشائعة،
from ripe fruits through chocolate malts
من الثمار الناضجة إلى حبوب الشوكولاته المخمرة
and barbecued ribs.
والأضلاع المشوية.
The other great principle of evolution
و المبدأ الأساسي الثاني في "نظرية التطور"
is sexual selection,
هو الانتقاء أو الاصطفاء الجنسي،
and it operates very differently.
وهو يعمل بشكل مختلف تماماً.
The peacock's magnificent tail
ذيل الطاووس الرائع
is the most famous example of this.
هو المثال الأكثر شهرة في هذا الموضوع.
It did not evolve for natural survival.
لم يتطور ليبقى في الطبيعة.
In fact, it goes against natural survival.
في الواقع فإنه يتعارض مع البقاء في الطبيعة.
No, the peacock's tail
لا، ذيل الطاووس الذكر
results from the mating choices
هو نتيجة لاختيارات التزاوج
made by peahens.
التي اتخذتها الطاووس الأنثى.
It's quite a familiar story.
هي قصة مألوفة إلى حد ما.
It's women who actually push history forward.
في الواقع المرأة هي التي تدفع التاريخ إلى الأمام.
Darwin himself, by the way,
بالمناسبة، داروين نفسه
had no doubts that the peacock's tail
ليس لديه أدنى شك بأن ذيل الطاووس الذكر
was beautiful in the eyes of the peahen.
كان جميلا في عيني الطاووس الأنثى.
He actually used that word.
لقد استخدم تلك الكلمة في الواقع.
Now, keeping these ideas firmly in mind,
الآن مع أخذ هذه الأفكار في عين الإعتبار
we can say that the experience of beauty
يمكننا القول بأن تجربة الجمال
is one of the ways that evolution has
هي إحدى الطرق التي استخدمتها نظرية التطور
of arousing and sustaining
لإثارة و إدامة
interest or fascination,
أهمية أو سحر
even obsession,
أو حتى الهوس
in order to encourage us
لتشجعنا
toward making the most adaptive decisions
في إتخاذ أكثر القرارت التكيفية
for survival and reproduction.
من أجل البقاء و التكاثر.
Beauty is nature's way
الجمال هي طريقة الطبيعة
of acting at a distance,
للتحرك عن بعد
so to speak.
إذا جاز لي التعبير.
I mean, you can't expect to eat
أعني لا أتوقع أن تأكل من
an adaptively beneficial landscape.
المناظر الطبيعية
It would hardly do to eat your baby
من الصعب أن تقوم بذلك لطفلك
or your lover.
أو لمن تحب.
So evolution's trick
إذاً براعة نظرية التطور
is to make them beautiful,
هي في جعل هذه المناظر جميلة
to have them exert a kind of magnetism
بحيت تتمتع بمغناطيسية
to give you the pleasure of simply looking at them.
تمنحك السعادة بمجرد النظر إليها.
Consider briefly an important source of aesthetic pleasure,
تأمل للحظه في مصدر مهم من المتعة الجمالية
the magnetic pull
الجذب المغناطيسي
of beautiful landscapes.
للمناظر الطبيعية الجميلة
People in very different cultures
الناس في ثقافات مختلفة
all over the world
في كل أنحاء العالم
tend to like a particular kind of landscape,
يميلون الى الإعجاب بنوع معين من المناظر الطبيعية
a landscape that just happens to be similar
قد يكون المنظر طبيعي مشابها
to the pleistocene savannas where we evolved.
لسافانا العصر البلستوسيني من حيث تطورنا
This landscape shows up today
هذا المنظر يظهر اليوم
on calendars, on postcards,
على التقويم، على البطاقات البريدية،
in the design of golf courses and public parks
في تصميم ملاعب الجولف و الحدائق العامة
and in gold-framed pictures
و في أطر ذهبية
that hang in living rooms
ُتُعلق في غرف المعيشة
from New York to New Zealand.
من نيويوك الى نيوزلنده
It's a kind of Hudson River school landscape
انه أقرب الى المناظر الطبيعية في مدرسة "نهر هدسن"
featuring open spaces
يضم مساحات مفتوحة
of low grasses
من العشب القصير
interspersed with copses of trees.
تتخللها كتل من الأشجار.
The trees, by the way, are often preferred
و بالمناسبة فإن الأشجار في الغالب مفضلة
if they fork near the ground,
اذا كانت متفرعة بالقرب من الأرض،
that is to say, if they're trees you could scramble up
وهذا يعني، يمكنك بوجود الأشجار أن تتسلقها
if you were in a tight fix.
لو كنت في مأزق شديد
The landscape shows the presence
المشهد يظهر وجود
of water directly in view,
الماء مباشرة في المنظر
or evidence of water in a bluish distance,
أو دليل لوجود الماء في المسافة المزرقة،
indications of animal or bird life
هي دلالات على حياة الحيوان و الطيور
as well as diverse greenery
فضلا عن خضرة متنوعة
and finally -- get this --
وأخيرا، تأمل هذا ..
a path
مسار
or a road,
أو طريق،
perhaps a riverbank or a shoreline,
ربما ضفة النهر أو شاطئ،
that extends into the distance,
الذي يمتد إلى مسافة،
almost inviting you to follow it.
و كأنه يدعوك لاتباعه.
This landscape type is regarded as beautiful,
هذا النوع من المناظر الطبيعية تعتبر جميلة،
even by people in countries
حتى الناس في بلدان
that don't have it.
لايملكون مثل هذه المناظر.
The ideal savanna landscape
المشهد المثالي السافانا
is one of the clearest examples
هو أحد الأمثلة الواضحة
where human beings everywhere
حيث البشر في كل مكان
find beauty
يجدون الجمال
in similar visual experience.
في تجربة بصرية مماثلة.
But, someone might argue,
ولكن، قد يقول شخص ما،
that's natural beauty.
هذا الجمال الطبيعي.
How about artistic beauty?
ماذا عن الجمال الفني؟
Isn't that exhaustively cultural?
أليست هذه ثقافية شاملة؟
No, I don't think it is.
لا، لا أعتقد أنه كذلك.
And once again, I'd like to look back to prehistory
ومرة أخرى، أود أن ننظر إلى الوراء إلى عصور ما قبل التاريخ
to say something about it.
أن أقول شيئا حيال ذلك.
It is widely assumed
ويفترض على نطاق واسع
that the earliest human artworks
أن الأعمال الفنية الأولية
are the stupendously skillful cave paintings
هي لوحات كهف مرسومه بشكل ماهر
that we all know from Lascaux
ونحن جميعا نعلم أن لاسكو
and Chauvet.
و شيفيت
Chauvet caves
كهوف الشيفيت
are about 32,000 years old,
لها ما يقارب 32000 سنة،
along with a few small, realistic sculptures
إلى جانب القليل من التماثيل الصغيرة والواقعية
of women and animals from the same period.
لنساء و حيوانات من نفس الفترة.
But artistic and decorative skills
لكن المهارات الفنية والزخرفية
are actually much older than that.
هي في الواقع أقدم من ذلك بكثير.
Beautiful shell necklaces
قلادات صدفية جميلة
that look like something you'd see at an arts and crafts fair,
التي تبدو وكأنها شيء يمكن أن تجده في معرض للفنون والحرف ،
as well as ochre body paint,
فضلا عن طلاء الجسم باللون الذهبي،
have been found
تم العثور عليها
from around 100,000 years ago.
من حوالي 100،000 سنة مضت...
But the most intriguing prehistoric artifacts
لكن أكثر تحف ما قبل التاريخ إثارة للاهتمام
are older even than this.
أقدم من هذه بكثير.
I have in mind
يدور في ذهني
the so-called Acheulian hand axes.
ما يسمى بمحاور الأيدي الأكليلينية
The oldest stone tools are choppers
أقدم الأدوات الحجرية القاطعة
from the Olduvai Gorge in East Africa.
من مضيق الاولدافي في شرق أفريقيا.
They go back about two-and-a-half-million years.
ترجع في الزمن إلى مايقارب اثنين ونصف مليون سنة.
These crude tools
هذه الأدوات الخام
were around for thousands of centuries,
كانت موجوده لآلاف القرون،
until around 1.4 million years ago
حتى حوالي 1.4 مليون سنة مضت
when Homo erectus
عندما بدأ الإنسان المنتصب
started shaping
بتشكيل
single, thin stone blades,
شفرات حجر رقيقة، احاديه
sometimes rounded ovals,
بعض الأحيان بيضاوية مستديرة
but often in what are to our eyes
ولكن في كثير من الأحيان، ما يظهر لأعيننا،
an arresting, symmetrical pointed leaf
ورقة متناظرة مدببه الشكل
or teardrop form.
أو على شكل دمعة.
These Acheulian hand axes --
هذه الفؤوس الأكلينيه
they're named after St. Acheul in France,
سميت تيمنا بالقديس اكيل في فرنسا،
where finds were made in 19th century --
حيث وجدت اكتشافات في القرن 19
have been unearthed in their thousands,
وقد اكتشفت بالآلاف،
scattered across Asia, Europe and Africa,
منتشرة في أنحاء آسيا وأوروبا وأفريقيا،
almost everywhere Homo erectus
الانسان المنتصب في كل مكان تقريبا
and Homo ergaster roamed.
وجابت الانسان العامل.
Now, the sheer numbers of these hand axes
الآن، الأعداد الهائلة من هذه الفؤوس اليدويه
shows that they can't have been made
يدل على أنها لم تصنع
for butchering animals.
لذبح الحيوانات.
And the plot really thickens when you realize
وتحبك المؤامرة حقا عندما تدركون
that, unlike other pleistocene tools,
بأنها على خلاف غيرها من أدوات العصر الجليدي،
the hand axes often exhibit
أن الفؤوس اليدويه غالبا ما لا تحمل
no evidence of wear
أي أثر للملابس
on their delicate blade edges.
على حواف شفراتها الحساسة.
And some, in any event, are too big
وبعضها، وعلى أية حال،كبيرة جداً
to use for butchery.
لاستخدامها للذبح
Their symmetry, their attractive materials
تناظرها ، موادها الجذابة
and, above all,
وقبل كل شيء،
their meticulous workmanship
صناعتها الدقيقة
are simply quite beautiful
هي ببساطة جميلة جدا
to our eyes, even today.
في ناظريَنا، حتى اليوم.
So what were these ancient --
إذا فما تلك الاشياء القديمة..
I mean, they're ancient, they're foreign,
أعني إنها قديمة و أجنية
but they're at the same time
ولكنها في نفس الوقت
somehow familiar.
مألوفة نوعا ما.
What were these artifacts for?
لماذا هذه القطع الأثرية ؟
The best available answer
الجواب الأفضل المتاح
is that they were literally
هي أنها كانت حَرفياً
the earliest known works of art,
أقدم الأعمال الفنية المعروفه ،
practical tools transformed
تحولت الأدوات اليدويه،
into captivating aesthetic objects,
إلى أشياء جمالية آسرة ،
contemplated both for their elegant shape
التفكير على حد سواء لشكلها الأنيق
and their virtuoso craftsmanship.
ومهارتهم الموهوبه.
Hand axes mark
أثر الفؤوس اليدويه
an evolutionary advance in human history --
تطور ثوري في تاريخ البشرية
tools fashioned to function
أدوات صنعت لأداء وظيفه
as what Darwinians call "fitness signals" --
كما يسميه الداروينين إشارات اللياقة البدنية
that is to say, displays
وهذا يعني، عروض
that are performances
و التي هي فعاليات
like the peacock's tail,
مثل ذيل الطاووس،
except that, unlike hair and feathers,
إلا أنه، على عكس الشعر والريش،
the hand axes are consciously
الفؤوس اليدويه
cleverly crafted.
تصنع بوعي و ذكاء.
Competently made hand axes
فؤوس صنعت بشكل مؤهل
indicated desirable personal qualities --
مما يشير الى صفات شخصية مرغوب فيها
intelligence, fine motor control,
ذكاء و قدره جيده في التحكم،
planning ability,
تخطيط للقدرات،
conscientiousness
اجتهاد
and sometimes access to rare materials.
والوصول أحيانا إلى المواد النادرة.
Over tens of thousands of generations,
لأكثر من عشرات الآلاف من الأجيال،
such skills increased the status
مثل هذه المهارات ارتقت بمكانة
of those who displayed them
الأشخاص الذين عرضوها
and gained a reproductive advantage
واكتسبوا الميزة الإنتاجية
over the less capable.
خلال أبسط قدرة
You know, it's an old line,
كما تعلمون ، انها طريقه قديمه،
but it has been shown to work --
ولكنها أثبتت فعاليتها--
"Why don't you come up to my cave, so I can show you my hand axes?"
"لماذا لا تأتي الى كهفي لأريك فؤوسي اليدويه"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Except, of course, what's interesting about this
ما عدا، بالطبع، ما يثير الاهتمام حول هذا
is that we can't be sure how that idea was conveyed,
هو أننا لسنا على يقين من كيفيه نقل الفكرة ،
because the Homo erectus
لأن الإنسان المنتصب
that made these objects
الذي صنع هذه الأشياء
did not have language.
لم يكن لديهم لغة
It's hard to grasp,
من الصعب فهم ذلك،
but it's an incredible fact.
لكنها حقيقه لا تصدق.
This object was made
صنع هذا الشيء
by a hominid ancestor,
من قبل أسلاف الانسان --
Homo erectus or Homo ergaster,
الانسان المنتصب أو الانسان العامل
between 50,000 and 100,000 years
بين 50 و 100000 سنة
before language.
قبل اختراع اللغة
Stretching over a million years,
تمتد على مدى ملايين السنين،
the hand axe tradition
تقليد الفأس اليدوي
is the longest artistic tradition
هو أطول التقاليد الفنية
in human and proto-human history.
في تاريخ البشرية والإنسان البدائي.
By the end of the hand axe epic, Homo sapiens --
بحلول نهاية فتره الفأس اليدويه، الانسان العاقل --
as they were then called, finally --
كما كانت تسمى آنذاك، وأخيرا...
were doubtless finding new ways
ومما لا شك فيه العثور على طرق جديدة
to amuse and amaze each other
لإمتاع و إدهاش بعضنا البعض
by, who knows, telling jokes,
من خلال إلقاء النكات،
storytelling, dancing, or hairstyling.
رواية القصص، الرقص ، أو تصفيف الشعر.
Yes, hairstyling -- I insist on that.
نعم، تصفيف الشعر -- أنا أصر على ذلك.
For us moderns,
بالنسبة لنا الأشخاص العصريين،
virtuoso technique
الموهوب تقنياً
is used to create imaginary worlds
يستخدم لخلق عوالم خيالية
in fiction and in movies,
في الخيال والأفلام،
to express intense emotions
للتعبير عن المشاعر الجياشه
with music, painting and dance.
بالموسيقى، اللوحات والرقص.
But still,
ولكن لا يزال،
one fundamental trait
سمة أساسية واحدة
of the ancestral personality persists
من السمات السلفيه استمرت
in our aesthetic cravings:
في رغباتنا الجماليه
the beauty we find
الجمال الذي نجده
in skilled performances.
في العروض ذات الحرفيه العاليه
From Lascaux to the Louvre
من اسكو لمتحف اللوفر
to Carnegie Hall,
إلى قاعة كارنيجي،
human beings
البشر
have a permanent innate taste
لديهم ذوق فطري دائم
for virtuoso displays in the arts.
في عروض الفن المبدع.
We find beauty
نجد الجمال
in something done well.
في شئ منجز بدقه
So the next time you pass a jewelry shop window
لذا في المرة القادمة التي تمر فيها بنافذة متجر مجوهرات
displaying a beautifully cut
ويعرض فيها قطع جميلة
teardrop-shaped stone,
على شكل دموع
don't be so sure
لا تكن متأكداً
it's just your culture telling you
بأن فقط ثقافتك التي تخبرك
that that sparkling jewel is beautiful.
بأن هذه الجوهرة المتألقه جميلة.
Your distant ancestors loved that shape
أحب اجدادكم القدماء هذا الشكل
and found beauty in the skill needed to make it,
و وجدوا الجمال في الحرفة التي تتطلب صنعه
even before
حتى قبل ذلك
they could put their love into words.
كان بمكنهم التعبير عن حبهم بالكلمات
Is beauty in the eye of the beholder?
هل الجمال في عين صاحبه
No, it's deep in our minds.
لا انه عميق في أذهاننا
It's a gift handed down from the intelligent skills
انه هبه، قدمت الينا من الحرف الذكيه
and rich emotional lives
و الحيوات الغنية بالعواطف
of our most ancient ancestors.
لأجدادنا القدماء
Our powerful reaction to images,
رد فعلنا القوي على الصور،
to the expression of emotion in art,
و التعبير عن العواطف في الفن،
to the beauty of music, to the night sky,
وجمال الموسيقى الى سماء الليل
will be with us and our descendants
سوف تكون معنا وذريتنا
for as long as the human race exists.
لطالما وجِدَ الجنس البشري.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)